Inventory of the Moisés Hassan M. papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Moisés Hassan M. papers
1930-2007
2002C4
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
The Moisés Hassan M. papers contain materials relating to Nicaragua during and after the Sandinista revolution of 1979. Moisés Hassan Morales was a prominent figure in the Sandinista National Liberation Front (FSLN) and participated in the armed struggle against the Somoza dictatorship. He occupied a number of posts in the Sandinista government formed after the overthrow of Anastasio Somoza, and subsequently served as mayor of Managua. Hassan Morales later broke with the FSLN and its leader Daniel Ortega over what Hassan Morales perceived to be the increasingly authoritarian and corrupt tendencies of the Sandinista government. His collection consists of personal correspondence; speeches and writings; correspondence and other documents relating to his time in government; and photographs.
Hassan M., Moisés
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002, with some materials added subsequently.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
José Ovidio Puente papers, Hoover Institution Archives
María Haydeé Terán papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1942 Born
1968 Receives doctorate in physics from the University of North Carolina at Raleigh
1979 Fights as a Sandinista commander in the uprising against the rule of Anastasio Somoza
1979-1985 Holds various posts in the Nicaraguan government. Makes official visits to Czechoslovakia, East Germany, and the Soviet Union
1985-1988 Serves as mayor of Managua
1988 Resigns from the Sandinista National Liberation Front
2009 Author, La maldición de Güegüense
Scope and Content of Collection
The Moisés Hassan M. papers contain materials relating to Nicaragua during and after the Sandinista revolution of 1979. Moisés Hassan Morales was a prominent figure in the Sandinista National Liberation Front (FSLN) and participated in the armed struggle against the Somoza dictatorship. He occupied a number of posts in the Sandinista government formed after the overthrow of Anastasio Somoza, and subsequently served as mayor of Managua. Hassan Morales later broke with the FSLN and its leader Daniel Ortega over what Hassan Morales perceived to be the increasingly authoritarian and corrupt tendencies of the Sandinista government. His collection consists of personal correspondence; speeches and writings; correspondence and other documents relating to his time in government; and photographs.
The small correspondence series includes a 1985 letter addressed to the Sandinista commander and minister of the interior, Tomás Borge, in which Hassan Morales enumerates his criticisms of the Sandinistas for fostering what he describes as an atmosphere of "opportunism and servility." The disillusionment of Hassan Morales with the Sandinistas is described in more detail in his memoirs, drafts of which can be found in the Speeches and Writings series of the papers. They also provide a broader account of the role played Hassan Morales in the uprising against Somoza, his participation in the post-revolutionary Junta of National Reconstruction, and his time as mayor of Managua. The memoirs were published in book form in 2009 as La maldición de Güegüense.
Materials relating to the period in which Hassan Morales participated in the Sandinista government are collected in the Government of Nicaragua file. These are arranged in a general file, as well as by governmental department, and include routine correspondence, reports, and a small number of Ministry of the Interior case files. There are also a few country dossiers produced by the Department of International Relations. Documents pertaining specifically to the FSLN are grouped in the Sandinista National Liberation Front file and include correspondence, instructions, reports, and organizational plans.
The prints in the Photographs series of the papers record a number of foreign visits made by Hassan Morales in his capacity as a Sandinista official. There are also numerous prints that depict the final stages of the Sandinista revolution, including scenes of FSLN fighters entering the town of Léon and the capital Managua.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series: Correspondence; Speeches and Writings; Government of Nicaragua file; Sandinista National Liberation Front file; Subject file; and Photographs
Nicaragua--Politics and government--1979-1990.
- Correspondence, 1980-1990 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Alvarez, Javier, 1988 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Borge, Tomás, 1985 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1989 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Embassy of the United States, Consular section (Managua, Nicargua), 1989 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Koch, Edward I., 1988 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Morales S., Jorge A., 1987 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Ortega Saavedra, Daniel, 1981-1989 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Ortíz Sequeira, Pedro, 1987 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Riza, Iqbal, 1990 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Wheelock R., Jaime, 1981 (Folder 1: 10)
- Speeches and Writings, 1980-2005 (Box 1-2)
  Contains articles, monograph, and speeches, arranged chronologically
  - "A cuatro meses del triunfo Sandinista," En marcha, 1980 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Speech commemorating Sandinista Revolution, Managua, Nicaragua, 1980 March 2 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Speech on natural resources in Nicaragua, 1980 April 23 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Speech on social security, 1980 July 17 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Speech on Latin American economy, 1980 December 4 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Speech on role of physical education and sports, Managua, Nicaragua, 1983 March 12 (Folder 1: 17)
  - With William Ratliff, "Breaking Nicaragua's Cycle of Failure?", 2001 December (Folder 1: 18)
  - La maldición de Güegüense, 2004-2007 (Folder 1-2)
    - First draft, 2004 (Folder 1: 19-26)
    - Second draft, 2007 (Folder 2: 1-2)
      - Typescript, 2007 (Folder 2: 1)
      - Compact disc containing text of draft, 2007 (Folder 2: 2)
- Government of Nicaragua file, 1979-1986 (Box 2-3)
  Contains correspondence, itinerary, lists, and reports, arranged in a general file by physical form, and dossiers, case files, and correspondence, arranged by government department, and by physical form thereunder
  - General, 1979-1986 (Folder 2-3)
    - Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Folder 2)
      - 1979 (Folder 2: 3)
      - 1980 (Folder 2: 4-7)
      - 1981-1983 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Itinerary, 1980 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Lists of government ministers, 1979-1980 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Reports, 1980-1981 (Folder 3)
      - Sugar industry, 1981 (Folder 3: 1)
      - Tourism, 1980 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Department of International Relations, 1986 (Folder 3)
    - Country dossiers, 1986 (Folder 3)
      - Belgium, 1986 (Folder 3: 3)
      - North Korea, 1986 (Folder 3: 4)
      - Soviet Union, 1986 (Folder 3: 5)
      - Spain, 1986 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Ministry of the Interior, 1979-1980 (Folder 3)
    - Case files, 1979-1980 (Folder 3)
      - Acosta, Edgar, 1979 (Folder 3: 7)
      - Mendoza López, Joaquín, 1980 (Folder 3: 8)
      - Silva Morazón, Carlos, 1979 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Folder 3: 10)
- Sandinista National Liberation Front file, 1979-1982; 3 (Box 3)
  Contains correspondence, instructions, plans, reports, and a pamphlet, arranged by physical form
  - Correspondence, 1979-1982 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Instructions, plans, and reports, 1979-1980 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Pamphlet, 1980 (Folder 3: 13)
- Subject file, 1979-1997; 3-4 (Box 3-4)
  Contains campaign literature and reports, arranged by subject
  - Frente Patriótico Nacional, 1979 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Managua (Nicaragua)--Economic policy, 1979-1980 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Movimiento de Acción Renovador, 1990-1997 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Movimiento de Unidad Revolucionaria, 1989 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Nicaragua--Economic conditions, 1979-1992 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Nicaragua--Politics and government, 1990 (Folder 4: 4)
- Photographs, 1930-1980; 4 (Box 4)
  Contains prints arranged by subject and chronologically thereunder
  - Hassan M., Moisés, 1979-1980 (Folder 4)
    - With Daniel Ortega, Sergio Ramírez, and other Sandinista leaders, 1979 (Folder 4: 5)
    - With fighters of the Sandinista National Liberation Front, 1979 (Folder 4: 6)
    - With Fidel Castro, other Cuban officials, and members of the Nicaraguan delegation visiting Cuba, Havana, Cuba, 1979 July 25 (Folder 4: 7)
    - With other delegates at the inaugural meeting of COPPPAL (Conferencia Permanente de los Partidos Políticos de Latinoamérica y del Caribe), Oaxaca, Mexico, 1979 October 12 (Folder 4: 8)
    - With Rainer Offergeld, Managua, Nicaragua, 1979 November 14 (Folder 4: 9)
    - With Fidel Castro, Daniel Ortega, Humberto Ortega, Sergio Ramírez, and other Nicaraguan officials, Managua, Nicaragua, 1980 (Folder 4: 10)
    - With Pham Van Dong, Daniel Ortega, and other Nicaraguan officials, Managua, Nicaragua, 1980 (Folder 4: 11)
    - With Tomás Borge and various officials during a visit to Czechoslovakia, 1980 (Folder 4: 12)
    - With Yasser Arafat, Managua, Nicaragua, 1980 (Folder 4: 13)
    - With Humberto Ortega, Tomás Borge, and various officials during a visit to the Soviet Union, 1980 (Folder 4: 14)
    - With Humberto Ortega, Tomás Borge, and various officials during a visit to East Germany, 1980 March (Folder 4: 15)
    - With Alexander Lilov, Managua, Nicaragua, 1980 December 23 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Others, 1930-1979 (Folder 4)
    - Sandino, Agusto, 1930 (Folder 4: 17)
    - Protest against the rule of Luis Somoza, New York City, 1959 (Folder 4: 18)
    - Somoza, Anastasio, Managua, Nicaragua, 1979 (Folder 4: 19)
    - Various scenes of the Nicaraguan Revolution, including Sandinista fighters, 1979 (Folder 4: 20)
- Incremental Materials (Box 5)